Maitraye Das

maitraye@u.northwestern.edu

Research Statement

My research interest falls broadly in the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), and Accessibility. Specifically, my doctoral research involves studying and designing for accessible collaborative content production in ability-diverse teams. My work draws on literature in HCI, CSCW, and critical disability studies to uncover how accessibility is created, negotiated, and sustained in collaborative work. Methodologically, I take a multi-stage approach that includes qualitative methods (e.g., contextual interviews, observations, ethnography) as well as system design, development, and evaluation through controlled experiments and design exploration studies. As a HCI researcher, my broader goal is to support accessibility through design and thus, contribute towards reducing equity gaps in education, employment, and creative expression.

Education

NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

EVANSTON, IL, USA

PhD in **Technology and Social Behavior** (Computer Science & Communication) Fall 2017 - Present *Dissertation:* Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments *Committee:* Darren Gergle (chair), Anne Marie Piper (co-chair), Marcelo Worsley, and Cynthia Bennett

NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

EVANSTON, IL, USA

MS in **Technology and Social Behavior** (Computer Science & Communication) *GPA*: 3.97 out of 4.00

Mar 2021

BANGLADESH UNIVERSITY OF ENGINEERING & TECHNOLOGY (BUET) BANGLADESH

BS in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) with Honors Sep 2015

GPA: 3.85 out of 4.00 (top 6% of the graduating class)

Research Experience

COLLABORATIVE TECHNOLOGY LAB | NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY | Fall 2017 - Present Graduate Research Assistant | advised by Darren Gergle

- Conducted contextual interviews and observations to understand collaborative writing practices and accessibility needs of visually impaired writers. Developed audio enhancements for asynchronous collaborative writing and evaluated through a mixed-methods controlled experimental study. Currently developing non-visual interactions to support accessibility in synchronous collaborative writing for visually impaired writers. [CSCW 2019]
 Faculty collaborator: Anne Marie Piper
- Collected a dataset of nearly 0.45 billion edits by 2000 OpenStreetMap editors using Python and Osmium. Performed quantitative analysis to investigate gender-based self-focus bias in OpenStreetMap. [CHI 2019]

Faculty collaborator: Brent Hecht

INCLUSIVE TECHNOLOGY LAB | NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY Spring 2018 - Present Graduate Researcher | advised by Anne Marie Piper

Conducted ethnographic field observations and contextual interviews at a weaving studio for people
with vision impairments. Designed auditory augmentations on a loom to enhance collaborative weaving
among blind weavers and their sighted instructors. Currently developing an audio-tactile system to
support collaborative designing of fabric patterns for blind weavers. [CHI 2020, TACCESS 2021]

ABILITY TEAM | MICROSOFT RESEARCH, USA

Summer 2020

Research Intern | mentored by John Tang

Conducted semi-structured interviews with 36 neurodivergent professionals. Performed thematic
analysis to highlight accessibility issues in remote work during the COVID-19 pandemic. [CSCW 2021]
Collaborators: Kathryn Ringland, Anne Marie Piper

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, USA

Summer 2017

Researcher (remote) | mentored by Moushumi Sharmin and Shameem Ahmed

 Performed a systematic literature review on the design of smart technologies for children on the autism spectrum. [CHI 2018]

BANGLADESH UNIVERSITY OF ENGINEERING & TECHNOLOGY

Aug 2014 - Sep 2017

Undergraduate Researcher | advised by Tanzima Hashem

 Developed a secret sharing algorithm for privacy-preserved and authenticated queries in genomic databases to compute disease susceptibility. [COMPSAC 2018, Journal of Information Processing 2019]

Honors, Awards, & Grants

PhD Student Research Award Dept of CS, Northwestern University	2021
Graduate Research Grant Northwestern University (\$2,999)	2021
Finalist (top 20) Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship	2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award ACM CHI [C1]	2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award ACM CSCW [J4]	2019
Special Recognition for Outstanding Review ACM CHI'21 (3 times), ACM CSCW'19	2021, 2019
Conference Travel Grant Northwestern University (\$2,300 + \$1,500)	2019, 2018
Best Paper Award IEEE COMPSAC [C4]	2018
Student Travel Grant ACM UbiComp (\$600)	2018
Student Scholarship Grace Hopper Celebration, USA	2018
Best Undergraduate Thesis Award CSE, Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2015
Best Technical Poster Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014
Student Scholarship Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014
Dean's List Award Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2011 - 2015
University Merit Scholarship Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2011 - 2014

Journal Articles¹

- Journal / II trotos

- J1. **Maitraye Das,** Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. Design and Evaluation of Collaborative Writing Techniques for People with Vision Impairments. Under review in *ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI)*. [Impact Factor: 3.147]
- J2. Maitraye Das, John Tang, Kathryn E. Ringland, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Towards Accessible Remote Work: Understanding Work-from-Home Practices of Neurodivergent Professionals. In Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Vol. 5, CSCW1, Article 183 (April 2021), 30 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3449282
- J3. Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, Maitraye Das, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Melodie: A Design Inquiry into Accessible Crafting through Audio-Enhanced Weaving. In ACM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS), Vol. 14, 1, Article 5 (March 2021), 30 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3444699 [Impact Factor: 2.641]

¹ <u>Top-tier publication venues in Human-Computer Interaction</u> research include peer-reviewed conferences such as CHI and CSCW and journals such as TOCHI. Since 2018, CSCW transitioned to a hybrid journal structure. These venues are highly selective, extensively reviewed, and intended for archival papers only. When available, the acceptance rate is included.

- Q J4. Maitraye Das, Darren Gergle, and Anne Marie Piper. 2019. "It doesn't win you friends":
 Understanding Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments. In
 Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Vol. 3, CSCW, Article 191 (November 2019), 26
 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3359293 [acceptance rate: 31.2%]
 *Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions).
 - J5. Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, **Maitraye Das**, Tanzima Hashem, Sharmin Afrose, and Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar. 2019. Towards Privacy-preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries. In *Journal of Information Processing*, Vol. 27, (September 2019), pp. 624-642. DOI: 10.2197/ipsjiip.27.624

Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers

- **Q** C1. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Weaving by Touch: A Case Analysis of Accessible Making. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20)*, 1-15. DOI: 10.1145/3313831.3376477 [acceptance rate: 24.3%] *Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions).
 - C2. **Maitraye Das,** Brent Hecht, and Darren Gergle. 2019. The Gendered Geography of Contributions to OpenStreetMap: Complexities in Self-Focus Bias. In *Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '19)*, Paper 563, 14 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3290605.3300793 [acceptance rate: 23.8%]
 - C3. Moushumi Sharmin, Monsur Hossain, Abir Saha, **Maitraye Das**, Margot Maxwell, and Shameem Ahmed. 2018. From Research to Practice: Informing the Design of Autism Support Smart Technology. In *Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '18)*, Paper 102, 1-16. DOI: 10.1145/3173574.3173676 [acceptance rate: 25%]
- P C4. Maitraye Das, Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Sharmin Afrose, Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar, and Tanzima Hashem. 2018. A Novel Secret Sharing Approach for Privacy-Preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries in Genomic Databases. In Proceedings of the 42nd IEEE International Conference on Computers, Software, and Applications (COMPSAC '18), pp. 645-654. DOI: 10.1109/COMPSAC.2018.00097

 [acceptance rate: 24%]

 *Best Paper Award

 **Best Paper Award*

 *
 - C5. Abir Saha and **Maitraye Das**. 2017. Impact of Social Networking on Post-Partum Depression in Women: An Analysis in the context of Bangladesh. In *Proceedings of the 20th IEEE International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '17)*, pp. 1-6. DOI: 10.1109/ICCITECHN.2017.8281831
 - C6. **Maitraye Das** and Abir Saha. 2017. An Automated Speech-Language Therapy Tool with Interactive Virtual Agent and Peer-to-Peer Feedback. In *Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE '17)*, pp. 510-515, DOI: 10.1109/ICAEE.2017.8255409
 - C7. Fatema Khan, **Maitraye Das**, and Ahiya Ahammed. 2016. PurpleAid: An mHealth platform to combat health hazards of women. In *Proceedings of the 2016 International Conference on Medical Engineering, Health Informatics and Technology (MediTec '16)*, pp. 1-6. DOI: 10.1109/MEDITEC.2016.7835368
 - C8. **Maitraye Das**, Sunandita Sarker, and Syeda Lammim Ahad. 2016. A Novel Health Support System with Biometric Data Acquisition Device. In *Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '16)*, pp. 201-206. DOI: 10.1109/ICCITECHN.2016.7860195

Refereed Workshop Short Papers, Posters, and Doctoral Consortia

- 1. **Maitraye Das.** 2020. Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In 2020 Conference Companion Publication on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '20). DOI: 10.1145/3406865.3418369 [Doctoral Consortium]
- 2. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Rethinking Power and Politics in Accessible Making. In *ACM CHI Workshop "Nothing About Us Without Us": Investigating the Role of Critical Disability Studies in HCI.*
- 3. **Maitraye Das.** 2019. Who Can See What: Privacy and Audience Management for People with Vision Impairments on Social Media. In ACM CSCW Workshop on Addressing the Accessibility of Social Media.
- 4. **Maitraye Das**. 2018. Understanding Collaborative Writing Practices of People with Visual Impairments. In *Proceedings of the 2018 ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp '18*), pp. 1744-1749. DOI: 10.1145/3267305.3277807
- 5. **Maitraye Das**. 2018. Towards Understanding the Effects of Social Networking on Postpartum Depression in Women. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing*, USA.
- 6. **Maitraye Das**, Sharmin Afrose, and Tanzima Hashem. 2015. Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing*, USA.
- 7. **Maitraye Das**, Sunandita Sarker, and Shahina Ferdous. 2014. SpeechAid: A Self-treatment System for Individuals with Speech Disorder. In *Grace Hopper Celebration India*. *Best Technical Poster Award

Teaching Experience

UNITED INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY (UIU)

DHAKA, BANGLADESH

Lecturer | Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

Oct 2015 - Mar 2017

• Instructed courses on Computer Architecture, Digital Logic Design, Electrical Circuits and Assembly Programming Language.

Skills

Programming: Python, R, C, C++, Java, HTML, CSS

Research Methods: Interviews, contextual observations, ethnography, thematic analysis, grounded theory method, survey design, experiment design, quantitative analysis, prototyping

Students Mentored

Thomas McHugh Undergrad in Computer Science, Northwestern University	2020 - Present
Rawan Mohamed Undergrad in Computer Science, Northwestern University	2020
Caroline Brewley High school student researcher	2019
Nusrat Jahan Mozumder Undergrad in CSE, Bangladesh University of Engg. & Tech	2017 - 2018
Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar Undergrad in CSE, Bangladesh University of Engg. & Tecl	h 2017 - 2018
Fatema Khan Undergrad in CSE, United International University	2016
Ahiya Ahammed Undergrad in CSE, United International University	2016

Invited Talks

Input and Interaction (INFO 463) | University of Washington

Nov 2020

• Guest lecture: Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments (virtual)

Bangladesh HCI and ICTD Study and Research Group, Virtual Event

Apr 2020

■ Talk: Designing for Accessible Interaction

Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship Finalist Presentation | Redmond, WA, USA Nov 2019

Poster: Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments

Academic Services

Program Committee Member Shadow PC, ACM COMPASS Grace Hopper Conference, HCI Track	2021 2021
Reviewer ACM CHI [*outstanding review recognitions: 3] ACM CSCW [*outstanding review recognition: 1] IEEE COMPSAC ACM DIS Grace Hopper Conference Australasian Database Conference	2021 2019-2021 2021 2020 2017 2016
Student Volunteer ACM CHI ACM CSCW ACM UbiComp InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University Publicity Co-chair	2019, 2021 2019 2018 2018
InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University Outreach & Memberships	2019
Co-host & Co-organizer Inspiring Stories (podcast series on Bangladeshi women in STEM)	2020 - Present
Member Northwestern Graduate Women in Computing Association for Computing Machinery (ACM), SIGCHI, SIGACCESS Bangladeshi Women in Computer Science and Engineering	2019 - Present 2017 - Present 2015 - Present
Code Coach Volunteer BraveCamp Chicago (non-profit coding camp for high school girls)	Summer 2018
Vice-President Murchhona : BUET (cultural club)	2014 - 2015